Tamara Paula Temple

Webologist and Software Craftsperson

♦) +1-651-485-2195
 ⋈ tamara@tamouse.org
 † https://tamouse.org
 y tamouse
 ⊕ tamouse

Summary

Deeply experienced in software design and development methodologies, especially related to the disciplines of software quality, web applications, user experience, and team building. Presently working at the intersection of Rails, GraphQL, and React, developing modern web applications with fast response times.

Skills

general software engineering, web development, business analysis, consulting, facilitating, teaching software software engineering software engineering frontend, low-level design, coding, debugging, testing, tool chains

web Rails, Sinatra, Django, Flask, Express, web libraries React, GraphQL, ApolloClient

frameworks ApolloServer, JAMstack, Gatsby

databases PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite, MongoDB, Redis Ruby, JavaScript, Perl, Shell, Python 3, PHP, HTML5, CSS3, SCSS/SASS,

HAML, C/C++
tlify, nginx, puma, AWS ECS, EBS, static site jekyll, middleman, gatsby

servers Netlify, nginx, puma, AWS ECS, EBS, static site jekyll, middleman, gatsby S3, Cloudfront generators

tools Emacs, Webstorm, RubyMine, rake, thor, yeoman (yo), webpack, babel, npm/npx, gulp, make testing Minitest, RSpec, Jest, Testing Library

Methods Program architecture and design; User-/task-centered design; Test-/behaviour-driven development; Structured analysis, design, development, and testing; Process flow analysis, systems theory, cybernetics; Object-oriented analysis, design, programming, and testing; Agile development, scrum master; Continuous everything: integration, testing, deployment; Precision elicitation and facilitation, communication for action

Education

1975-1980 Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 3.2 GPA.

Additional Structured analysis, design, programming and testing, System testing, Objected oriented analysis, design, programming and testing, Consulting and facilitating skills, Neuro-linguistic programming certified practitioner, Project management, Public speaking and presentation skills, You Don't Know JS with Kyle Simpson, Advanced JavaScript, Numerous courses through FrontendMasters.com on React, Webpack, GraphQL, JAMstack, Angular, others

Experience

2017-2020 API-driven Rubyist, React/GraphQL Maven, ReachLocal (Gannett), Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Implement modern GraphQL APIs in Ruby for the Kickerv product, and develop replacement React web client using GraphQL interface with Apollo Client.

- work on the Kickserv product
- o build robust APIs to enable modern web client applications for desktop and mobile to access backend data
- migrate API to use GraphQL in Ruby
- o create a React web client using Apollo to talk GraphQL to the back end application
- fix defects in existing frontend software
- o deployments to AWS ECS via terraform
- work with other engineers to build common components

2001-present Web Developer, Pontiki Software Crafts, Mendota Heights, Minnesota.

Freelance web design and development, including pro bono work for non-profits and individuals desiring a presence on the Web. Includes finding hosting space, development of information architecture, design layout of site, development and/or repurposing of content, and maintenance.

- User experience and User-centered design for interactive web sites
- Database design for dynamic web sites and applications
- Creation and developing on frameworks for generating static web sites
- Frameworks and infrastructure to implement business logic and web site features
- Environments and tools for development, testing, integration and deployment
- Teach and coach new developers, running "Toast & Tech" study groups
- O Volunteer mentor/coach/instructor for Women Who Code Twin Cities, Hack-the-Gap, Code Switch (Code for America)

2016-2017 Contract Software Developer, Software for Good, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Provide software to enable clients to query a large datastore with natural language and return meaningful datasets.

- write anisble and shell scripts to deploy project to staging
- write training questions and entity extraction code
- write extraction, transfer, and load scripts for external data
- o provide code review and expertise to other project members
- wrote mainly in Python
- deployments using Ansible to AWS

2013-2016 Contract Software Developer, Ackmann-Dickenson, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Contract development in the areas of Rails and JavaScript on several A-D projects.

- Pro subscriptions and e-commerce in Brewtoad
- One-button recipe ordering in Brewtoad
- Customer Onboarding
- Micro-service architecture and implementation
- Angular SPA clients for MSA backend
- Massive and complex data analysis product

- O Data ETL middle layer to provide a massive speed-up for an e-commerce website
- Lots of Ruby on Rails and JavaScript
- o Deployments using chef, puppet, and ansible to Rackspace and AWS EBS

1980-present

Various positions, Hewlett-Packard, Shopzilla, NovuHealth, BluewaterBrand.

Career as a software developer, business analyst, process and technology consultant, author, facilitator, trainer

- Web development in PHP, JavaScript, Ruby on Rails
- Software development on unix system software
- Taught relationship-based skills to engineers, managers, and senior execs.
- Consulted with various software development groups within Hewlett-Packard to improve software development capabilities
- Developed software for network management at Hewlett-Packard
- Software Quality Engineer manager of 10 engineers
- Software Quality Engineer